Register of the Edward Geary Lansdale papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Speeches and Writings, 1954-1984
  - "Introductory Comments on the Campaign," speech, seminar on the Huk campaign, Fort Bragg, North Carolina, mimeograph, 1961 June 15
  - "Lecture: Southeast Asia," speech, Army War College, mimeograph, 1958 December 3
  - "Lessons Learned, The Philippines: 1946-53," speech, interdepartmental course on counterinsurgency, Foreign Service Institute, mimeograph, 1962 September 26
  - Letter to the editor, Washington Post, typescript and letter, 1971 August 16
  - Letter to the editor, Washington Post, typescript, 1972 June 16
  - Letter to the editor, Washington Post, typescript, 1972 July 8
  - Letter to the editor, Washington Post, typescript, 1972 September 2
  - Letter to the editor, Washington Post, typescript, 1975 May 2
  - Letter to the editor, Washington Post, 1977 January 31
  - Letter to the editor, World View, printed copy, 1977 May
  - "Liberty Hall," memorandum, typescript, 1963 November 29
  - "Limited War," symposium contribution, U.S. Air Force Academy, typescript, correspondence, and contributions by others, 1978 October 20
  - "The Local Scene Abroad," typescript, 1963 December 12 (Box 80)
  - "Military Policy in Underdeveloped Areas," informal discussion with Colonel Valeriano, Philippine Military Attache, typescript notes, 1957 February 27
  - "Military Psychological Operations," speech, Armed Forces Staff College, Norfolk, Virginia, mimeograph, 1960 January 7
  - "Military Psychological Operations: Part Two," speech, Armed Forces Staff College, Norfolk, Virginia, mimeograph, 1960 March 29
  - "A Moral Somewhere," Washington Post, typescript and printed copy, 1972 February 13
  - "Notes on Magsaysay," holograph, undated
  - "Our Battleground in Asia," seminar, Harvard University, typescript, 1957 June 19
  - "Pacification," typescript, undated
  - "People in Field," holograph, undated
  - "People's Wars," typescript, 1973 January 15
  - "Political Struggle in the Vietnam War," presentation, U.S. Air Force Academy, holograph, 1981 September 30
  - "A Political Warfare Lesson," typescript, 1954 April
  - "The Psychological Edge," holograph and notes, 1980 June 27
  - "The Refugee Strategy: 'A Fabrication,'" typescript and printed copy, 1975 April 11
  - Review of Alan Dawson, 55 Days, holograph, typescript, and correspondence, 1978 April
  - "Revolutions I Have Known," typescript, printed copy, and correspondence, 1975 Winter
  - "Revolution: Made in U.S.A.," holograph, undated
  - "Soldiers and the People," speech, Special Warfare School, Fort Bragg, North Carolina, mimeograph, 1962 August 30
  - "Some Comments on Vo Nguyen Giap," typescript and letter, 1973 March 12
  - "Some Possible Initiatives by the U.S. in re: Viet Nam," memorandum, 1975 April 6
  - "Some Thoughts About Central America," typescript, 1983 May 10
  - "Some Thoughts About Dave Sternberg," eulogy, typescript and letter, 1979 October 31
  - "Some Thoughts About the Retirement of Fritz Kraemer," typescript and letter, 1978 May
  - "Some Thoughts on the 100-Day Speech," holograph, undated
  - "Some Thoughts on Instability in Developing Countries," speech, National War College, typescript, 1974 November 25
  - "Some Thoughts on Strategy in the Vietnam War," unpublished paper presented at a colloquiem at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy, 1974 May
    Holograph, typescript, program, miscellany, partial transcript, correspondence, and mimeograph copies of contributions by others.
  - Speech, typescript, circa 1965 (Box 81)
  - Speech, typescript, 1980 May 4
  - Speech, Air War College, "Elements and Developments of Insurgency," mimeograph and correspondence, 1972 January 18
  - Speech, Army War College, typescript and correspondence, 1973 February 20
  - Speech, Panel on "The U.S. Military in Non-Military Warfare," National Strategy Seminar, National War College, mimeograph, 1959 July 23
  - Speech, Principia Conference on Vietnam, Elsah, Illinois, mimeograph, 1965 April 9
  - Speech, UCLA Student Colloquium, Los Angeles, California, holograph, 1966 May 6
  - Speech notes, Huk campaign, Fort Bragg, North Carolina, holograph, 1976 May 31
  - Speech notes, interdepartmental seminar, Foreign Service Institute, holograph, 1964 May 4
  - Speech notes, Maxwell AFB, holograph, 1964 January 31
  - Speech notes, Maxwell AFB, holograph, 1965 March
  - Speech notes, USMC-Quantico, holograph, undated
  - "Thoughts About a Past War," introduction to The War For Vietnam by Allan R. Millett, typescript, printed copy, correspondence, and preface by Millett, 1977 June
  - "Thoughts on Vietnam," typescript, 1964 December 31
  - "The Three Systems of Forces," typescript, undated
  - "The 'True American,'" speech, mimeograph, 1960 June 3
  - "A Trauma to Heal," notes and typescript, 1980 August 11
  - "Two Steps to Get Us Out of Vietnam," Look, holograph, typescripts, printed copy, and correspondence, 1969 March 4
  - "The U.S. Army's Public Relations in the Philippines," typescript, 1948 May
  - "Vietnam," speech, Yale University, typescript, 1964 November 23
  - "Vietnam: A Positive Way," typescript, 1965 January 26
  - "Vietnam: A Test of American Understanding of Revolution," mimeograph, 1964 August 8
  - "Vietnam and Beyond--Our American Role in the Pacific," speech, typescript, circa 1968
  - "Vietnam: Do We Understand Revolution?," Foreign Affairs, draft, typescript, printed copy, 1964 October
  - "Vietnam: Still the Search for Goals," Foreign Affairs, printed copy and correspondence, 1968 October
  - "Virginian Hearts and Minds: The Vietnamese Issue," typescript and letter, 1975 April 21
  - "Whither Vietnam?," typescript, 1968
- Subject File, 1943-1987
  Articles, unpublished papers, and miscellaneous items collected by Lansdale on a variety of topics, particularly Vietnam and the Vietnamese conflict, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Miscellany (Box 9)
  - Miscellany, material withheld pending declassification review
  - Atlantic Council
  - Bolt, Beranek, and Newman, Browne and Shaw International Studies Division
    - "Competence in International Defense Studies,", undated
    - "Technical Proposal for Research on Military Civic Action,", 1969 June 20
  - Bui Anh Tuan [see also: CORRESPONDENCE/Bui Anh Tuan]
  - Bunker, Ellsworth, correspondence and miscellany, 1979-1987
  - Cambodia
    - General, clippings, 1970-1984
    - Ministry of Plan, "Kompong Som--Future Seaport of Cambodia,", 1958 June
    - "Visit to Cambodia," memorandum, 1971 July 26-August 3
    - You in Cambodia, pamphlet, Commander-in-Chief, Pacific, and Chief MAAG, Cambodia, undated
  - Central America, memoranda, pamphlet, clippings, and letters, 1973-1986
  - Centre des Hautes Etudes de L'Armement
  - Chapelle, Dickey, printed material and correspondence with Elizabeth Deakman, 1982-1986
  - China
    - General, printed material, circa 1966-1979
    - Brohm, John F., "Lessons for Civic Action--The Experience of the People's Liberation Army,", undated
    - Fairbank, John K., "The People's Middle Kingdom," Foreign Affairs, 1966 July
    - Katzenbach, Edward L., Jr., and Gene Z. Hanrahan, "The Revolutionary Strategy of Mao tse-Tung," Political Science Quarterly LXX: 3, 1955 September
    - Koo, Y. C., "Confucianism and the World Crisis," address, China Institute, New York, "POL--Communist Chinese Doctrine," memorandum, excerpts from manifesto by Lin Piao, 1964 March 23, 1965 December 1
    - "The United States and China after Mao," conference, Washington, D.C., 1976 November 30
  - Communism. "Notes on Communism and the Cold War," Military Assistance Institute, Department of Defense, Washington, D.C., undated
  - Council on Foreign Relations
    - General, correspondence and miscellany, 1969-1979
    - "America and the Philippines--Asset or Liability?," George E. Taylor Carnegie Research Project, 1957-1958
    - "Basic Aims of U.S. Foreign Policy," study prepared at the request of the Committee on Foreign Relations, U.S. Senate, 1959 November 25
    - International Affairs Fellowship Program, competition, 1970-1971
    - The Middle East and U.S.-Soviet Relations, 1971 (Box 10)
    - Nielson, Waldemar A., "The Great Powers and Africa," New York: Praeger, 1969
    - Study Group on United States Relations with the Philippines. Papers, agenda, and official correspondence, 1957 October - 1958 February
  - Critchfield, Richard
    - "A Few Reflections," The Alicia Patterson Fund, New York, 1970
    - "Hello Mister! Where Are You Going?," parts one and two, The Alicia Patterson Fund, New York, 1971
    - "How Lonely Sits the City," parts one and two, The Alicia Patterson Fund, New York, 1970
    - "It's a Revolution All Right," The Alicia Patterson Fund, New York, 1971 May 2
    - "The Marginal Men," The Alicia Patterson Fund, New York, 1971 July 10
    - "A New Country: Conclusion of a Two-Year Study," The Alicia Patterson Fund, New York, 1971 August 1
    - "Sketches of the Green Revolution," parts one through four, The Alicia Patterson Fund, New York, 1970
  - Cuba, correspondence, speech, notes, and clippings, 1964-1984
    Includes material relating to Operation Mongoose.
  - East Pakistan (Box 11)
    - "A Manual for Rural Public Works," Director, Pakistan Academy for Rural Development, Comilla, East Pakistan, 1962 August
    - "Works Programme Through Basic Democracies, 1963-64," Government of East Pakistan, Basic Democracies and Local Government Department, section IV
  - Economic development, correspondence and writings by Dana Reynolds and others, 1968-1981
  - Food for Peace
    - "Fact or Fallacy?," memorandum for Dick Reuter, 1964 July 31
    - "Long-Range Impact, FFP, III," memorandum for Dick Reuter, 1964 May 7
    - "The Ocean," memorandum for Dick Reuter, 1964 May 1
    - Staff list
    - "Year-End Report of the Food For Peace Program, and Outlook for the Year 1963,", undated
  - Freedom Studies Center, Boston, Virginia
  - French, Jerome T., "Foreign Assistance in Crisis Situations,", 1968 August 5
  - Guerrilla warfare
    - "Operations Against Guerrilla Forces," Marine Corps Landing Force Development Activities, 1962 July
    - "The Third Challenge: Unconventional Warfare," Alert No. 6, Department of Defense, 1962 November 16
  - Harris, William R., "Intelligence and National Security," Harvard University, 1968
  - Higgins, Marguerite, Our Vietnam Nightmare, proofs, New York: Harper and Row, 1965
  - India, letter, memorandum, and reports by Alan Berg, 1967-circa 1969 (Box 12)
  - Indonesia
    - Acheh, National Liberation Front. "Attention to All American, Australian and Japanese Employees of Mobil and Bechtel,", 1977 October
    - Acheh, state of
      - Cabinet, 1977 October 30
      - Declaration of Independence of Acheh, Sumatra, 1976 December 4
      - Ministry of Education, Tiro, Tengku Hasan M. di, "The Drama of Achehnese History, 1873-77,", 1978
      - Ministry of Foreign Affairs, statement on ASEAN, 1977 October
    - "Democracy for Indonesia," U.S. Joint Publications Research Service, JPRS:6318, 1960 November 28
    - Nasution, A. H., "Principles of Guerrilla Warfare," Djakarta, 1954
    - Pelzer, Karl J., "The Agrarian Conflict in East Sumatra," Pacific Affairs, XXX: 2, 1957 June
    - Rogin, Gilbert, "Wanted! Guys for the Boondocks," Sports Illustrated 17: 24, 1962 December 10
    - Tiro, Hasan Muhammad di
      - "Neo-Colonialism in Indonesia," address to the United Nations Sixteenth General Assembly, 1961 October 1
      - "Statement by the Representative of the Federal Republic of Indonesia on Mr. Sukarno's Appearance Before the General Assembly of the United Nations,", 1960 October 3
  - Institute for Defense Analyses, Consultant Security Briefing, 1968 January
  - Insurgency and counterinsurgency
    - General, printed material, correspondence, and a mimeograph report entitled "A Study of Limited Wars,", 1966-1987
    - "Area Studies in Insurgency," Volume 4, USAF Special Operations School, undated
    - Bjelajac, Slavko N., printed article and mimeograph copy of "Guidelines for Measuring Success in Counterinsurgency,", 1964-1966
    - "Counterinsurgency: A Symposium, April 16-20, 1962," S. T. Hosmer, Chairman, S. O. Crane, Rapporteur, report prepared for the Advanced Research Projects Agency, RAND Corporation, 1963 January
    - Fall, Bernard, lecture, Far East Training Center, Hawaii, 1966 December
    - "Introduction to Insurgency," USAF Counterinsurgency course, volume one, 1971
    - Leighton, Richard M., and Ralph Sanders, eds., Insurgency and Counterinsurgency: An Anthology, Washington, D.C.: Industrial College of the Armed Forces, 1962 October (Box 13)
    - Peterson, A. H., G. C. Reinhardt, and E. E. Conger, eds. "Symposium on the Role of Airpower in Counter- insurgency and Unconventional Warfare," RAND Corporation, 1963 July
      - "The Algerian War"
      - "The Philippine Huk Campaign"
      - "Unconventional Warfare in the Mediterranean Theater"
    - Polk, Dr. William R., "Environment of Insurgency," paper presented at the National War College, Washington, D.C., 1971 February 5
    - Reinhardt, George C., ed., "Bibliographic Notes for Special Warfare Symposium,", undated
    - Turner, Alvin Charles, "The Police Role in Counter- insurgency Operations," dissertation presented to the faculty of the Graduate School, John Jay College of Criminal Justice, 1970 April 15
    - Wolf, Charles, "Insurgency and Counterinsurgency: New Myths and Old Realities," RAND corporation, 1965 May
  - Intelligence, printed material, newsletters, and correspondence, 1965-1977
  - International Study Group on Freedom and Democracy, first meeting, Paris, 1961 December 11-15
  - Japan
    - Japanese prints
    - Komatsu, Kyo, "A Japanese Franc-Tireur Talks with Gide and Malraux," reprint, The Centennial Review IV:1
  - Johnson Foundation, Racine, Wisconsin
  - Korea
    - General, clipping and issues of Korea Economic Digest, 1944-1970
    - Biderman, Albert D., "American Prisoners in the Korean War: An Antidotal Review," draft, 1961 February 5 (Box 14)
  - Laos
    - General, letter and a copy of "Brief Fact Sheet on USIS in Laos,", 1959-1986
    - Briefing notes on the Royal Kingdom of Laos, U.S. Information Service
    - General materials from Hank and Anne Miller
    - History of Laos, U.S. Joint Publications Research Service, 1958 October
    - Ministere de l'Education Nationale, Kene, Thao, Bibliography of Laos, 1958
  - LaRouche, Lyndon, letter and printed issuances, 1984
  - National War College (Box 18)
    - Lecture series, 1970 August-September
    - Lodge, George Cabot, "Political and Psychological Aspects of Modernization in the Developing World," speech, National War College, Washington, D.C., 1971 February 3
    - Materials for elective course on problems of the developing countries, 1974-1975
    - Materials for course on national power in the modern world, 1970
    - Pye, Dr. Lucian W., "Sociological and Economic Aspects of Modernization in the Developing World," speech, National War College, Washington, D.C., 1971 February 1
  - Peru, "Peruvian Community Development Program,", undated (Box 15)
  - Philippines
    - General, printed material, newsletters, correspondence, writings, reports, and miscellany, 1960-1987
    - Castillo, Leonel J., "Filipino-National Veterans of World War II," memorandum to Lansdale, 1978 February 4
    - Constitution of the Republic of the Philippines, proposed, 1972
    - Cuaderno, Miguel, luncheon in honor of, New York, 1957 October 1
    - House of Representatives, Committee on Anti-Filipino Activities. Roces, Joaquin R., "The Huk Situation," and "The Why and the Wherefore,", 1957
    - Huk movement
      - General, clipping, correspondence, and a mimeograph copy of Lavinia N. Hansen, "Successful Counterguerrilla Warfare--Magsaysay and the Philippine Huks: A Case Study,", 1966-1985
      - De Joya, Antonio R., "What After Amnesty?,", undated
      - "Huk Campaign in the Philippines," memorandum to General Le Van Kim, 1963 November 27
      - Valeriano, Colonel Napolian, speech, undated
      - Vargas, Jesus, and Tarciano Rizal, "Communism in Decline: The Huk Campaign," SEATO, undated
      - Ward, W. T. T., "The Guerrilla Resistance Movement in Central Luzon, About October 26, 1944, a Report to Allied Forces About to Invade,", undated
    - Joint U.S. Military Advisory Group to the Republic of the Philippines, general information and briefing brochure, 1959 January-February
    - Magsaysay, Luz, "No Politics for Mrs. Magsaysay,", undated
    - Magsaysay, Ramon
      - Borg, Parker W., "The United States and Ramon Magsaysay," unpublished paper, 1965 January 25
      - Postage stamp, U.S., in honor of Magsaysay, 1957
      - "The Ramon Magsaysay Award,", 1957 April
    - Ravenholt, Albert, "The Philippine Republic: A Decade of Independence,", 1957
    - Roces, Joaquin P., "The Philippines: The Trials of a New Nation," speech, 1959 February 24
    - Soliongco, I. P., "Seriously Speaking," reprint, Manila Chronicle, 1959 February 11
    - Starner, Dr. Frances, "Reluctant Partnership," Far Eastern Economic Review XLVII: 8, 1965 February 25
    - Sycip, Albino Z., "U.S. Aid and Philippine Claims,", 1959 January
    - World War II damage payments by U.S. to Philippines, bill authorizing, 1962
  - Singapore, Ravenholt, Albert, "Singapore's Peoples Action Party," paper presented at American Universities field staff conference, University of Alabama, 1968 December 12-13
  - Southeast Asia (Box 16)
    - "Asia, South X East," magazine prospectus, undated
    - "Asian Development--After Viet Nam," transcript, luncheon held at the Hotel America, 1968 August 27
    - Johnson, Lyndon B., "Pattern for Peace in Southeast Asia," speech, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Maryland, 1965 April 7
    - Mansfield, Mike, "Report on Indochina," Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1954
    - Moffat, Abbot Low, statement before the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, 1972 May 11
    - O'Donnell, John B., "Observations of Hawaiian Elections by Political Leaders From Asia,", 1968 September 10
    - Pelzer, Kenneth, "The Resource Pattern of Southeast Asia," reprint, South Asia in the World Today, Phillips Talbot, ed., Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1950
    - Reynolds, Dana D.
      - "Building Political Bases for Vietnam and Asian Development in Vietnam, Asia, the U.S. and Other Cooperating Countries," notes from luncheon discussion, Washington, D.C., 1969 April 17
      - "Emergency Program for Peace and Development in Southeast Asia," International Center for Dynamics of Development, 1971 March 29
      - "'Popular Participation' in Country Development," a resume of two years' dialogue, Washington, D.C.: Society for International Development, Committee on Political Development, June 1968, "Re: Washington 'Policy' Focus on 'Popular Participation,'", 1969 February 3
    - Rusk, Dean, "The Situation in the Western Pacific,", undated
  - Sweet, Charles F., "Assisting International Development," Washington, D.C.: Development Alternatives, Inc., 1970 August 20
  - Thailand
    - General, clipping and tourist information
    - "Revolution in Thailand,", 1958 October 20
  - Tuan, Bui Anh [see: Bui Anh Tuan]
  - United States Agency for International Development, Asia Training Center
    - "Asia Training Center Debriefs Concerning Vietnam: An Analysis and Report by USAID-CORDS Task Force,", 1970 February
    - "Draft Proposal-Center for Democratic Development-- Project IX,", 1968 May
  - United State military, correspondence, clippings, memoranda, and miscellany, 1969-1974
  - Vietnam
    - General (Box 17)
    - Bibliography
      - Coates, Joseph, Bibliography of Vietnam, Institute for Defense Analysis, 1964 January
      - Vietnam, Bibliography, revised edition, Sacramento State College, 1970 July 23
    - Cao Dai religion
      - "The Outline of Caodaism," fourth edition, 1967
      - "Recent Cao Dai Political Activities,", 1968 June 8
      - Song Than, "Full Details on the Murder of Cao-Dai ex-Lt. General Nguyen Van Thanh,", 1972 November 24
    - Democratic Republic of Vietnam, printed material and letters, 1976-1984
    - Diem, Ngo Dinh [see: Ngo Dinh Diem]
    - "Life in a Vietnamese Urban Quarter,", 1966
    - French involvement, printed article with comments by Joe Redick, 1972
    - Hoa Hao University, correspondence, flyer, miscellany, and mimeograph copy of Frisco W. Short, "The Influence of Small Religious/Political/Military Groups on National Politics: A Case Study [of] The Phat Giao Hoa Hao Republic of Viet Nam,", 1974
    - Luu Duc Trung, chronology of activities, undated
    - National Voluntary Service, Saigon, 1965-1966
    - Ngo Dinh Diem [see also: Politics and government; Republic of Vietnam]
      - General, correspondence, proofs, and printed material, 1973-1984
      - "The Beleaguered Man," Time LXV: 14, 1955 April 4 (Box 18)
      - Crozier, Brian, "The Diem Regime in Southern Vietnam," Far Eastern Survey XXIV: 4, 1955 April
      - Dickey, 2nd Lt. William P., "South Viet-Nam Under Ngo Dinh Diem," dissertation submitted to the faculty of the Graduate School of Georgetown University, 1965 January
      - "Mr. Diem Loses Favor," The Economist, 1955 October 8
      - "An Ex-Parachutist Officer Recounts How the Coup of November 11 Had Been Completely Aborted Before It Began,", undated
      - O'Daniel, Lt. Gen. John W., "When I Think of Ngo Dinh Diem,", 1963 November 5
      - Record albums of music composed in honor of President Ngo
      - Tran Van Don, memoirs and letters, 1972
      - Warner, Dennis, "Barbed Wire, Barred Gates...and the Mystic Mandarin They Isolate,", undated
    - Poetry and literature
      - Nguyen Phuoc Thien, "The Twelve of Us, a Poem,", undated
      - Tuong Van Nguyen-be
        - "Chung-Thuy,", 1966 June
        - "Study of the New Essence of Life Chung- Thuy,", 1968
      - Vu Van Tu, fiction
    - Politics and government
      - General, 1959-1974
      - Buddhists and Citizens Force, leaflet, with English translation, undated
      - Buddhists, leaflet, Vietnamese with English translation, 1967 Spring
      - Dai-Viet Revolutionary Party, manifestos
      - Democratic Bloc, Central Executive Committee, 1961 May
      - Democratic Youth of Vietnam, proclamation and "Fundamentals of Democratic Struggle,", undated
      - Front for Democratization (Box 19)
        - Dang Van Sung, "To the Vietnamese Nationalist Leaders: A Contribution to a Common Way Out of the Present Dilemma in Vietnam,", 1963 July
        - Proclamations and writings
      - Hoang Van Lac, Colonel, "A Solution to the Problem of Vietnam," partial translation, 1966
      - National Revolutionary Movement (NRM), rules and regulations, 1954
      - National Salvation Front, declaration, undated
      - "The Nationalist Cause and the Conditions of Fight After the Geneva Accords in 1954,", undated
      - "Nationalist Politics in Vietnam,", undated
      - Nguyen Khai, "National Sovereignty," translation, Student Forum Magazine, Dalat University, 1966 April
      - Nguyen Thai, "The Invisible Government of the Republic of Vietnam" [see also: CORRESPONDENCE/Nguyen Thai and Mai], undated
      - Oka, Takashi, letters to Richard H. Nolte of the Institute of Current World Affairs
        - 1964 December 7 - 1966 May 31
        - 1966 June 4 - 1967 June 4
      - Pond, Elizabeth, newsletters written as Alicia Patterson Fund fellow
        - "The Chau Trial I: Prologue,", 1970 March
        - "The Chau Trial II: Denouement,", 1970 April/July
        - "The Chau Trial III: Aftermath,", 1970 October
        - "Portrait of a Revolutionary," parts one and two, 1970 September
        - "Student Protest,", 1970 April
        - "Vietnamese Politics: Longer Term,", 1969 October
        - "Vietnamese Politics: Short Term,", 1969 September
    - Printed matter, articles, 1961-1971